<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tvvo Godly and notable sermons preached by the excellent and famous clarke, master Iohn Caluyne, in the yere. 1555 The one concernynge pacience in aduersitie: The other touchyng the most comfortable assurance of oure saluation in Chryste. Iesu. Translated out of Frenche into Englyshe.</title>
            <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1560</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4462</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112718</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847963</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847963</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13033</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69062)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13033)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 238:13, 1599:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tvvo Godly and notable sermons preached by the excellent and famous clarke, master Iohn Caluyne, in the yere. 1555 The one concernynge pacience in aduersitie: The other touchyng the most comfortable assurance of oure saluation in Chryste. Iesu. Translated out of Frenche into Englyshe.</title>
                  <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[104] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By VVyllyam Seres dvveling at the vvest ende of Paules churche at the sygne of the hedgehogge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1560?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon; suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G⁴ (-G4).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks leaf D1; some pages poorly filmed on UMI microfilm reel 238.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at UMI microfilm reels 238 and 1599 (British Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13033:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13033:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> TVVO <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> GODLY AND NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TABLE SERMONS PREACHED BY THE</hi> excellent and famous Clarke, maſter Iohn Caluyne, in the yere .1555. The one concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge Pacience in aduerſitie: The other touchyng the moſt comfortable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuraunce of oure ſaluation in Chryſte. Ieſu.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Frenche into Englyſhe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13033:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13033:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſten Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Monge the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde, ſounde, and moſte holſome leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whiche are taughte vs in the heauenly ſchole of our Sauiour Ieſus Chryſt, there be none that the holy goſt in more erneſt wiſe requyreth vs to learne, or that more maketh for oure comforte here and in the worlde to come, then to haue quietneſſe of mynde in aduerſytie, and to be aſſured of eternal ſaluation in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu. For<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> (though all trouble for the preſent tyme be greuous) yet lyke as when we pacyently run the race that is ſet before vs, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duryng ſuche correction and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement as our heauenly father leyeth vpon vs, he then cauſeth
<pb facs="tcp:13033:3"/> the ſame to turne ſo much to our profyte, and to bringe vs ſo qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ete fruite of ryghtuouſenes, that we thereby obteyne more of hys holyneſſe, and become veſſelles more apt to ſerue the glory of his name, and to edifye his churche: Euen ſo, of all conſolations and comfortes, this is moſt incompa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1. 2. Tim. 1 Mat. 25</note> that throughe the mooſte graciouſe purpoſe of the eternall God, oure euerlaſtynge ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſo certayne and ſure, that it was determyned and decreed by hym in Chryſt Ieſu his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſonne, before the foundation of the worlde was leyed.</p>
            <p>Touchynge theſe two poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: namely, the quiet or pacient ſufferynge of trouble in Chriſtes cauſe. And the aſſuraunce of our eternall ſaluation in hym, thou
<pb facs="tcp:13033:3"/> haſt here (gentle reader) two no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table, godly and comfortable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, made by goddes faythful ſeruaunt, maiſter Iohn Caluine euen at ſuch tyme as here in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, the ſworde of tyrannye was full of bloudde, and the fyre burnynge hotte. By the whiche worthy ſermons, we all be cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon: partly to choſe rather to ſuffre aduerſitie with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> then to enioy the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſynne for a ſeaſon: And partely in nothynge to reioyſe ſo muche, as in that our names are wrytten in heauen.<note place="margin">Luc. 10.</note> As we be taughte by oure ſayde ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne lorde and maſter Chryſt Ieſus, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for euer ⸫ Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13033:4"/>
            <head>Sondaye the .v. of May. 1555. in the forenone.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2. Tim. 1</bibl> 
                  <p>¶ Be not therfore aſhamed to teſtify our Lord, neither be aſhamed of me which am bounde for his ſake: but be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the afflyctions of the goſpell, through the power of god, who ſaued vs, and cauled vs with an holye cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, not accordyng to oure dedes, but accordynge to his owne purpoſe and grace, whiche grace was geuen to vs, throgh Chriſt Ieſus before the world was: but is nowe declared. &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthoughe that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty God hath in his ſonne ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye<note place="margin">Io. 17. 1. Co. 2. Ephe. 3.</note> manyfeſted his glorye and maieſtye throughe his ſpirite and goſpel, wherethroughe he is of all the worlde to be honored and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhypped, yet is mannes vnkinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſuche, that he nedeth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall exhortation, to be nothing
<pb facs="tcp:13033:4"/> ſhamed of that goſpel. And why? for though god by his word cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all creatures to hym ſelfe, yet<note place="margin">Mat. 13. Mar. 4. Luke. 8.</note> the more parte rebel, diſpiſe and diſpyte the doctrine wherby he wold be knowen and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped: Seynge then, men are ſoo proude, peruerſe and frowarde,<note place="margin">Pſ. 74.</note> as to eleuate theym ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt theyr creatour, let vs not withſtanding take ſure holde of this place of ſcrypture here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that is,<note place="margin">Luc. 9.</note> that we be not aſhamed of the goſpel. And why? becauſe it is the teſtimony of our god, whiche we as nyghe as in vs lyeth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> ſhoulde publyſhe and declare, that al may be referred to this ende, that he be knowen and gloryfied as he is worthye. For when the goſpel is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, it lyeth as it were buryed.
<pb facs="tcp:13033:5"/> Wherefore he apoynteth<note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes bearers, to teſtifye the ſame vnto vs. And therfore let vs ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der vnto hym this honoure, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe the whole world went aſtraye,<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 2. Ti. 2.</note> that we abyde faſte by this holſome doctryne: for S. Paule ſetteth here forthe hys owne parſon, not for that he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for our approbation, but to declare, that<note place="margin">Mat. 10 1. Teſ. 4</note> when we ſeperate oure ſelues from goddes ſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, it is a ſufficient teſtymonie, that the maiſter is alſo forſaken and geuen ouer. Some parad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture wyl thincke, that in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakyng the myniſter of the word of god beynge tormented, diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted and in diſtreſſe, he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken but a mortall man:<note place="margin">Heb. 10, 2 Tim. 4</note> but god is therwith alſo diſpleaſed, in as muche as the man whiche
<pb facs="tcp:13033:5"/> ſo is troubled, bereth the marke of the goſpell, for goddes cauſe there throughe is declared, as it were betrayed. Saynct Paule therfore conſydering this: ſayth notably to Tymothee,<note place="margin">2. Ti. 1.</note> be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of me. And to ſay the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, as I haue alredy declared, one myghte laughe Tymothe to ſcorne, and ſende hym backe to his mayſter, as the wycked can full well ſpye theyr aduauntage at ſuche tymes, when god hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth hys ſeruauntes, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them to be vniuſtly tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">2 Pa. 36 Pſal. 35.78.79.</note> for then they aſſaulte and hardely laie at them which haue maynteined theyr doctrine. Here by mayſt thou ſee that Tymothe myghte be in doubte what to do, and therfore ſaith Sainct Paul vnto him, althoughe I be made
<pb facs="tcp:13033:6"/> as it were<note place="margin">1. Co. 4.</note> an outcaſt in the face of the worlde, ſo as ſome laugh me to ſkorne, others deteſte and hate me, yet be not thou therfore euer a whit the ſoner moued. For I am (ſayth he)<note place="margin">Ep. 3.4. Col. 4.</note> the pryſoner of Ieſus Chryſte, As who wolde ſaye, thoughe the whole worlde wolde laye to my charge all the vyllany that coulde be deuyſed, yet do they it not for myne offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for my cauſe is auouched in goddes preſence, and trulye the cauſe is his, for I ſuffer not for myne offences, his truethe is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes on my ſyde, when I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer perſecution, for that<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> I haue maynteyned and doo maynteyne the worde of God. Care not for the iudgement of the world, for men are led<note place="margin">Gene. 6. Pſa. 94</note> with frowarde af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Let it ſuffyce the then,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:6"/> that I be as it were an hoſtage for the ſonne of god, who hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth myne impryſonment, in ſuch wyſe, that thoughe the worlde thyncke it vyle and deteſtable,<note place="margin">Pſ. 116. 1. Pet. 1.</note> yet before god and his aungels it is not a lyttel eſtemed and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored. Nowe then, let vs lerne hereby in noo wyſe to defrawde Ieſus Chryſte of the teſtimonye<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.</note> which we ought of beare of him hauyng our mouthe ſhutte, when it ſhall be nedeful to<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> maynteine his honour and thactoritie of his goſpel: but contrary wyſe when we ſee our bretherne to be afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the name of god,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> we be founde redy to be cowpled wyth them, and that we ſtande in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence as much as in vs is, for the ſame cauſe,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> tremblynge or fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge nothynge at all, for al the
<pb facs="tcp:13033:7"/> ſtormes whiche myghte happen, thoughe the deuyll haue the bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell at wyll, and thoughe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were neuer ſo far oute of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.<note place="margin">1. Co. 15. Colo. 1.</note> Let vs always abyde ſted faſtly in our determynation, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we muſt beare wytnes of the ſon of god, ſeynge<note place="margin">Rom. 1. Phil. 2.</note> he wyll be ſerued of vs in a matter of ſuche weight and worthineſſe. But yet, let vs haue a ſpeciall eye, whether they ſuffer for theyr fautes, or for the teſtimonie of goddes truethe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge a ſpecyall regarde<note place="margin">1. Co. 16.</note> that we ſet not lyghte of any perſonne whom we ſhall perceaue for ſuch a cauſe to be oppreſſed. For<note place="margin">Ioh. 7. Phil. 1.</note> we maye not raſhely iudge in ſuche a caſe, leaſt thiniurie therof touche god hym ſelfe: we muſt therfore make dylygente inquiſition, to know the cauſe why men do ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.
<pb facs="tcp:13033:7"/> If wee perceyue they haue walked in an vpright conſcience, and neuertheles blamed, reuiled and tormented, and that for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of God, let that ſuffice the to blotte out all the obprobries of the worlde: for that is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherfore ſayncte Paule ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1</note> be thou partaker of the af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flyctions of the goſpell: for<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turallye, it is geuen to euery one of vs to ſpare gladly hym ſelfe: And thoughe we confeſſe, &amp; that without diſſymulation,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> that it is a ſyngular grace whiche God geueth when he wyl be ſerued of men for the mayntenaunce of his cauſe, yet is there noone whiche wolde not gladdely exempt hym ſelfe from perſecution. Wee can well prayſe *ſuche, as valiently offer them ſelues to the conflicte,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:8"/> (as the martirs of Ieſus Chriſt)<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> are worthy to be eſtemed &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured) yet in the meane whyle,<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note> there is none whiche wolde not gladly be farre of from the ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. And whye? becauſe we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte not this admonytion of ſ. Paule,<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 2. Ti. 3.</note> that is, that the goſpell bryngeth afflyctions. Iheſus Chryſte hauynge once ſuffered in his owne perſon,<note place="margin">Act. 14.</note> wyl nowe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo haue his doctryne coupled and ioyned to many miſeries: He can when it ſhall pleaſe hym, cauſe the goſpell to be receaued wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute contradiction, but what?<note place="margin">Act. 1. Luc. 1.</note> the holy ſcrypture muſt be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, whiche ſhall be declared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the middeſt of hys enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Men alſo muſt come vnto hym<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.</note> vpon this condition, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer many conflyctes, for as much
<pb facs="tcp:13033:8"/> as the wicked when god cauleth them, auaunce them ſelues and rebell agaynſte god,<note place="margin">Mar. 10 2. Tim. 3</note> it is then vnpoſſible for vs to enioy the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel without perſecution. Not for that the cooles are kyndeled and the faggottes alwayes ſet on fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but whether it be after one ſorte or other, it muſte come to paſſe, that<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> we be exerciſed, we muſt nedes (I ſay) fyght vnder oure Lorde Ieſus Chryſt. Now then, he whiche wolde gette him ſelfe a farre of from the croſſe of oure Lorde Ieſus Chryſte,<note place="margin">2. Ti. 2.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth he not his owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? where is the hope of lyfe, but in this ſacryfyce of the ſonne of god? for thus ſtandeth the caſe that he wyll be like vnto vs, and we muſt be transformed into his ſymilitude. Seynge then that it
<pb facs="tcp:13033:9"/> ſo is, let vs lerne to walke after that maner, ſeynge we are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto cauled, as heretofore wee haue ſeene, that ſuche is the plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure and wyll of God: we muſte then without farther diſputynge or contradyction,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.</note> bowe downe oure ſhoulders, and humble oure ſelues thervnto. Nowe lette vs farther ſee, what Saynct Paul here ſaythe: for he leadeth vs by degrees to the matter, in that he<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1</note> wolde not haue vs to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of our bretherne, when they be euyll ſpoken of, and rebuked of the worlde, but that we ſhulde be euer vnyted vnto theym: but howe maye that be? fyrſte he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, that the goſpell can not be without perſecution, as tofore is ſayd: it pleaſeth god<note place="margin">Mat. 10</note> that men be ſo deuyded: not but that God
<pb facs="tcp:13033:9"/> cauleth al men outwardly to the vnitie of faythe,<note place="margin">Luc. 14.</note> and the doctrine of<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5</note> the goſpell is the meſſage of reconſiliation. But yet note that the faythfull<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> are drawen by the hower of hys holye ſpirite,<note place="margin">Rom. 11</note> the vnfaythfull abyde in theyr hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of harte, as hereafter it ſhal be more at length intreated of.</p>
            <p>For as the fyer is kynled, when thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der being inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred in the aire bryngeth forthe a greate hurly-burly, ſo is it when the goſpel is preached. Nowe then if perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion followe the goſpell, and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſt wolde that to be<note place="margin">Colo. 1.</note> fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in his members which he ſuffered in his own perſon, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be (as it were) dayly cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed,<note place="margin">Mat. 10 16.</note> can it be lawfull for vs to withdrawe our ſelues from that ſtate? Seinge then that in the
<pb facs="tcp:13033:10"/> goſpell conſiſteth all hope of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that<note place="margin">Colo. 1.</note> theron we ſhuld ſtay our ſelues, let vs note what Saynct Paul ſayth, who wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs to<note place="margin">Rom. 12 Heb. 6.</note> ſtretche forthe oure hande towardes oure bretherne, when we ſee them oppreſſed, tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder fete, ſpit at, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp;<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> that we ſhuld rather deſire to be theyr companyons in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe all obprobries and vylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the worlde,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> then beynge honoured, had in reputation and credyte, to be alienated from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſuffer for the cauſe which is common to eyther of vs. This haue we then to lerne out of this place of ſcrypture, nowe becauſe on our behalfe we be weake, and thyncke we ſhould be ſwalowed vp, as it were throughe perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as ſone as we ar aſſaulted
<pb facs="tcp:13033:10"/> by the rage of the enemies,<note place="margin">Pſ. 74.</note> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we ſe to haue the ſwynge and power in the worlde. S. Paule addeth, that<note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> we ſhall not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of the aide ſuccour &amp; helpe of oure God, for when he ſendeth vs to the conflycte, it is not to try our force and ſtrength, but he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vs immediatelye, &amp; geueth vs an inuincible power to wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, and therefore addeth S. Paule: <hi>Accordinge to the power of God,</hi> to take awaye all excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of dyſcouragement. Euerye man (as I haue ſayd) wold haue a colour and cloke to withdrawe hym ſelfe from perſecutions, and ſaye. Oh, I wolde to god I had the grace to ſuffer for his names ſake, I acknowledge it to be the greatteſte benefyte that myghte happen to me, euery one (I ſaye)
<pb facs="tcp:13033:11"/> wyll confeſſe this, but they wyll adde, we are weake, we ſhal ſone be ouerthrowen, the tormentes wyll aſtonyſhe vs, ye ſe the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie and rage of thenemyes. Thus wyll euery one, after he hath confeſſed what an excellent thyng it is to ſuffer for the name of god, be neuertheleſſe quit. But S. Paule plucketh from vs all ſuche excuſes,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10</note> ſayinge that god ſhall be ready to ſtrengthen vs, for we may not reſpecte what is in our ſelues: For true it is that beſydes the inuations of our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes, there nedeth but oure owne ſhadowes to fraye vs: our owne conceyte were ſufficient to put vs to flyghte. But after we haue acknowleged oure weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, let vs come to the remedy: and when we beholde our owne
<pb facs="tcp:13033:11"/> infyrmities, and what a difficul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie we haue to withſtande our en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nemyes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50</note> let it be an occaſion to induce vs to call vpon god with all humbleneſſe for ayde: and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note> no maner of habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in our ſelues, let vs humblye caule vpon hym to ſtretche forth his hande, to thende he fayle vs not when we be brought to thex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremytee. And ſo (beynge at reſt) to acknowledge,<note place="margin">2. Co. 11.</note> that wee are more then feable, to thende that oure god prepare vs to thexamy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and trial. For that is the true conſideration of our weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: yt is (ſaye I) that we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlegynge oure infyrmities,<note place="margin">Mar. 9.</note> ſhoulde deſyre god to helpe our weakeneſſe, accordynge to that he knoweth to be meteſte for vs: for therevnto muſte we haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pecte.
<pb facs="tcp:13033:12"/> If this doctrine were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prynted in oure hartes without farther reaſonynge, wee ſhoulde be farre awaye better dyſpoſed to ſuffer then we are. But alas? there are verye fewe whiche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre this leſſon: naye, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that we wolde rather ſtop oure eares, and ſhutte oure eyes when we are ſpoken vnto therof, *we make wyſe that we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrous, that god ſhould ſtrenthen vs: but in effecte we can not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce oure ſelues to beholde this power, wherof S. Paule ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, preſumynge that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter toucheth vs not.<note place="margin">2. Co. 12</note> But yet do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the our lord teſtifie vnto vs, that his power ſhal be alwayes in vs and that we ſhal therof be poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And therefore let not our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be occatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to withdraw
<pb facs="tcp:13033:12"/> vs from the croſſe and perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſeyng that god<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note> hath taken the care of vs, to ſupplye that whiche wanteth in vs, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo promyſeth to do it. Nowe S. Paule taketh not heere the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of god, to trifle withall, but<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> he teſtifyeth to al faythful peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that it ſhall be redye and at hande when we deſyre the ſame, ſo ferforth as we deſyre to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; warded therwith to fight when the ſonne of god calleth vs to the conflycte,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 9</note> farthermore in aſmuche as men haue nede to be ſpurred forthe on all ſydes. S. Paule addeth here oone note to make vs aſhamed, if we be not feruently minded to glorifie Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſte, yea to ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution when it ſhall be ſoo his pleaſure to calle vs therunto, he
<pb facs="tcp:13033:13"/> ſayth, that<note place="margin">Tit. 2.3.</note> god hath ſaued vs, and hath cauled vs with an holy vocation, then if God throughe his infynyte goodneſſe hathe ſoo<note place="margin">Pſa. 59.</note> preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vs, is our ingratitude to be excuſed, if we on the other ſyde anſwere him not according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? beholde the goodneſſe of our God,<note place="margin">Pſa. 86 Oſee. 13</note> whiche hath drawen vs out of the goulfe of hell, wherin we were loſte and dampned,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.</note> he hath broughte vs the ſaluation, and hathe further cauled vs to make vs partakers therof. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then god ſheweth hym ſelfe thus lyberall, yf we on oure behalfe turne oure backes and wyll not voucheſafe to receaue the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which he offereth,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> were not that a poynte of malyce to farre out of ſquare? Let vs then take hede, howe ſayncte Paule goeth
<pb facs="tcp:13033:13"/> aboute to accuſe here, all ſuch as haue not byn conſtante and cora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyouſe to ſuffer all thaſſaultes, whiche for the goſpelles cauſe were layde on mennes ſhulders. So dothe he without doubte go aboute to<note place="margin">Rom. 1. Act. 14.</note> confyrme the hope of the faythfull, by openynge that whiche god hath alredy done for them: for when god hath ſhewed vs any euident token of his kind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, he dothe it to the ende<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.</note> we ſhould hope for the lyke an other tyme at his hande, vntyll he haue finiſhed that which he hath begun. If then god hath<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1</note> ſaued vs, and hath alſo cauled vs with an holye vocation, thyncke you that he wyll leaue vs in the mid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dle of the waye? when he hathe<note place="margin">Act. 14.</note> opened vnto vs the ſaluation, that he hath geuen vs legges to
<pb facs="tcp:13033:14"/> walke with, that he hath geuen vs his goſpell, by the whych he leadeth vs vnto his kyngdome, that he openeth the gate vnto vs: when he hath thus wrought with vs, ſhal we thynke, that he wyll then leaue vs there, and ſo mocke vs, and cauſe his grace to be vnprofitable, fruſtrate &amp; loſt? No, no,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. Phil. 1.</note> let vs hope, that he wil brynge his worke to perfection. Therfore let vs go on<note place="margin">Heb. 4.10.</note> boldely: for ſeyng god hath diſplayed one parcell of his power and myght towardes vs, let vs not doubt, but he wyll contynue alwayes<note place="margin">1. Co. 15.</note> to geue vs the perfecte victory ouer ſathan and al our ennemies ſo farre as we tary and abide vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll that Ieſus Chryſt<note place="margin">Col. 1.</note> who is oure headde and captayne, ſhewe hym ſelfe, that<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> all power and
<pb facs="tcp:13033:14"/> ſtrength is geuen him of god his father,<note place="margin">Mat. 28 Phil. 2.</note> to comunicate of the ſame vnto vs. We ſee nowe then, the meanynge of Sayncte Paule. Wherefore after we haue conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued what is the power of God, wherof we haue a lyttle before made mention, let vs immedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately adde this declaration whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che hath ben made. Trewe it is god hath in effecte and by expery<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence teſtyfyed vnto vs,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10 Heb. 13.</note> that he wyll neuer fayle vs at our nede, and why? for he hath alredy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs. Let vs then ſo depend of hym (ſeynge we are in the way) that he wyll ſurely bryng vs to ſaluation.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1</note> He hath cauled vs with an holye vocation, that is to ſaye,<note place="margin">Ioh 15.</note> he hath choſen vs vnto hym ſelfe, he hath ſeuered vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world, wherby he declareth
<pb facs="tcp:13033:15"/>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11</note> that he wolde not haue vs caſte awaye with the vnyuerſall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the worlde. For as muche then as oure lorde hathe thus withdrawen vs frome the wycked world,<note place="margin">Iſa. 40 62</note> wyl he not ſtill hold vs vnder his mighty arme and conducte vs vntill the ende? This then is a ſufficient confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the power of god: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we ſhall ſtyll fynde redye at hande to helpe vs,<note place="margin">Hebr. 3.</note> ſo farforthe as therein we put our confidence and truſte, callynge to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce how we haue alredy felt the ſame: But to make our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte of this doctryne effectually: fyrſte we muſte vnderſtand, that when god reueled his trueth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs,<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> it was an euydent teſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monye, that we<note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> alredye apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned to his heauenlye inhery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:15"/> that he wold avouche for his owne, and to be of his flocke. Nowe then, when we ſhall be hereof well perſwaded, &amp; in our ſelues well reſolued, then nede we not doubte to walke on conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nually and go forward. For<note place="margin">Pſa. 91.</note> we ſhal be vnder his protection and defence: for ſeynge he is of ſuche ſtrength to ſurmounte al our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> oure ſaluation can not but be in ſafe kepyng. Lette vs not then feare when we fele our infyrmitie, but<note place="margin">pſal. 37</note> let vs ſtay our ſelues vpon god, who wyll pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyde for vs, ſeynge he hath<note place="margin">Ioſu. 1. Heb. 13.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to aſſyſte vs. This hadde nede to be well borne away. Let vs therfore applye oure ſtudye, and ſee, that we take good hede to remember that whiche is here ſayde, for he wyll not fayle vs.
<pb facs="tcp:13033:16"/> Thus after many perſwaſions made for the ſtrengthenynge of vs agaynſte ſuche temptations, when we ſhal be at a full poynte that<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> god wyl finyſhe our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as he hath begunne,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.</note> aſſyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge vs in the myddle of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, in ſuche wyſe that wee ſhall with conſtancie ſurmounte them, and tryumphe ouer our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes, althoughe<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4 2 Cor. 4</note> it ſeemeth to the worlde that we are troden vnder feete, yea and vtterly ſwo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowed vp, then muſt we come to this declaration which Saynct Paule addeth, towchynge oure ſaluation and holy vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of we haue ſpoken. He ſaith that<note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> it is not for our deſertes, but ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordynge to the purpoſe of God and his grace. Hereby wyll he better admonyſhe vs, by decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:16"/> that oure ingratitude is ſo much the more to be condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note> in that that god hath opened the ineſtimable treaſors of his goodnes toward vs, for he hath had<note place="margin">Rom. 3. Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. 2.</note> no reſpecte to our worckes or dignite, when he called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to ſaluacion, it proceaded of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s fre grace. That was the cauſe wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he drewe vs to hym ſelfe. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> therefore the leſſe ſhalbe oure e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſe when we ſhall falſefye ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faithe, ſeynge that not onlye w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 9.</note> haue byn purchaſed throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the bloude of oure Lorde Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt his only begotten ſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that he alſo cared for our ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion before the creation of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> worlde.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phe. 1.</note> Let vs marke wel th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> howe S. Paul dothe here co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dempne our ingratitude,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebr. 3.</note> if w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be found vnfaithful to our god, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13033:17"/> ſtande not ſtoute to beare wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto his goſpell, when he thervnto cauleth vs. For<note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> wee be not ſaued accordynge to oure dedes (ſayth he) but according to his owne purpoſe and grace. S. Paule addeth, that that was ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen vs<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> before the worlde was, before the worlde had his courſe and begynnynge, but nowe hath it byn manyfeſted (ſayth he) at the commyng of oure lord Ieſus Chriſt. For when that great<note place="margin">Tit. 2.</note> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyoure appered, the grace which before was hid (yea not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by mans iudgement) was manifeſted and opened. And why? becauſe<note place="margin">Heb, 2.</note> the ſonne of god, ſettynge death at naught (ſaythe he) hath alſo brought an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal life. And we nede not to make long cyrcuytes to ſinde the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:17"/>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 3.</note> for the goſpell leadeth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducteth vs therunto. When ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore god ſendeth vs that meſſage of ſaluation, we muſt receaue the inheritaunce promyſed,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> we nede not trotte far of for it, for god ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs out, by whoſe grace we open our hartes and geue paſſage to this teſtimony of the goſpell &amp; immortalite of the heuenly king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome to dwell in vs, althoughe we be<note place="margin">Pſa. 103. Iob. 17.</note> poore and fraile veſſelles yea thoughe there be but corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and rottenneſſe in vs, yet ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehende we out of hand this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, and haue a<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> ſuffyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente teſtimonye acceptynge the grace whiche in the goſpell is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto vs. Herein is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the whole proceſſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſaynct Paule ſpeaketh. Now to vnderſtand better that whiche
<pb facs="tcp:13033:18"/> is here conteined, let vs note this worde <hi>Purpoſe</hi> to betoken the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtynge<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> Decree of god, not as thoughe the matters were to be caryed hyther and thyther: for when we ſpeake of the councel of god,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> we maye not alwayes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, who hath ſoo induced hym we may not imagyne reaſons, as to ſaye, for this cauſe hath god ſo determyned, or wherfore wolde he ſo do, but contrarye wyſe god wold haue vs<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 1. Pet. 1.</note> kepte vnder this modeſtie to thincke that his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wyll ſhoulde ſuffyce vs for rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, when he ſayth, god hath ſoo ordeyned. Althoughe the thynge ſeme ſtrange vnto vs, or that we coulde perceyue therin no appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante reaſon, yet muſte we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that his only wyl<note place="margin">Ro. 9. Pſa. 92.</note> is iuſt, and not to be reproued. That (ſay
<pb facs="tcp:13033:18"/> I) ſhulde be<note place="margin">Deu. 4.</note> al oure wyſedome, to ratifie al that for good, which god ordereth and diſpoſeth, with out ſayenge whye or wherefore. Nowe for as muche as men haue always ſuche tyklynge ſpirites, and geue them ſelues ouer much lybertie to theyr curioſities: S. Paule to abate ſuche boldeneſſe, bryngeth vs backe<note place="margin">2. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of god, into the whiche wee maye not enter ſo depelye, as to knowe who hath moued him, but alſo to note it as a weyghty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that<note place="margin">Pſa. 92.</note> his wyll is iuſte. Hereby then are we admonyſhed that oure ſaluation<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> dependethe not for the reſpecte of oure mery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, that god inquyred not what we were, nor whereof we were worthy, when he choſe vs to him ſelf. But he had his purpoſe, that
<pb facs="tcp:13033:19"/> is to ſaye, he ſought not without hym ſelfe the cauſe of oure ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for ſoo this worde purpoſe ſignifieth <hi>Decree.</hi> Sainct Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les mynde herein is euydent. but becauſe that men accordynge to theyr arroganſie, can not temper them ſelues except they imagine alwayes ſome dygnytie or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynes to be proper to theym ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and that theye well deſerue that god ſhoulde ſeke after them. S. Paule ſpecyally the better to<note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> exclude all that men can attry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute vnto them ſelues, ſayth, pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe and grace: which importeth as much as though he had ſayde, purpoſe freely. It ſerueth then to abate al our workes, to the ende we be no more ſoo folyſhe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynate as to thyncke, that God hath choſen vs, for anye thynge
<pb facs="tcp:13033:19"/> that was in vs. No no, for wee knowe<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> that god went not out of hym ſelfe when he choſe vs to ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation, for he ſawe<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> there was but dampnation in vs, he then contented him ſelf with his pure grace &amp; infinite mercy. Who<note place="margin">Pſa. 102.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdynge oure myſeries, wolde<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.</note> ſuccour and helpe vs, although we were not worthy therof. And for more ample confyrmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Sayncte Paule ſaythe that this grace was geuen vs<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> before all tymes. And herby ſe we, how men are<note place="margin">Eccle. 16.</note> depriued of their ſenſes when they wyl boſt them ſelues, and ſtand in theyr owne conceyt, that they bee the cauſe of theyr owne ſaluation, &amp; that they haue anticipated or preuented goddes goodneſſe: Nowe then, doth not oure ſaluation depend of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb facs="tcp:13033:20"/> election?<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> God choſe vs before we were, what could we then do, were we then apt veſſelles? were we then well diſpoſed to come to God? we ſe then that oure ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beginneth not from the time we had knowledge and diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſithens we were well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or mynded, oure ſaluation (I ſaye) beginneth not thens, but it is grounded vppon the eternall election of god whiche was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world was made. What coulde we then do? Had we the meanes to promote our ſelues? coulde we moue god to caule vs to hym ſelfe? and to ſeparate vs from the world? is there not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vs a greate blyndneſſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 10. Phil. 3.</note> as to thyncke in our ſelues ſome wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyneſſe, to exalte oure merytes to the obſcuryng and darkening
<pb facs="tcp:13033:20"/> of goddes grace, and that we can prepare our ſelues to haue acceſſe vnto him throughe our merites? wel then for what purpoſe hath ſayncte Paule ſet here the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of god, ſayeng, that the grace of god hath byn geuen vs before al tymes? but that ther through we are ſuffycientely admonyſed, that they whiche thyncke to abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyſhe the doctryne of the election of god, do adnichylate (as much as in them is) the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the worlde, and blot out by ſuche de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueliſhe ſuppoſtes and pillars, the vertue of the bloudde of our lord Ieſus Chryſte: to put all to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſion,<note place="margin">Gala. 1.</note> to ouerthrow the goſpel, yea, and vtterly to quenche and brynge out of memory the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of god, the deuyll hath noo meter proppes then ſuch as fight
<pb facs="tcp:13033:21"/> agaynſte predeſtination, whiche<note place="margin">Act. 13. 1. Teſſ. 2.</note> can not ſuffer in theyr deueliſhe rage, that the ſame be ſpoken of, and that this meſſage be publy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed as it ought. If we deteſt the papyſtes beynge moſt execrable, becauſe they haue prophamed al the holy ſcrypture, becauſe they haue peruerted and corrupted the trueth of the goſpell and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce of god, by infectynge al the worlde with ſuperſtition and ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrye, thothers are muche more deteſtable whiche go about to ſet at naught the ſprite of grace and election of god, and wold by cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; peruerſe wayes<note place="margin">He. 10.29 1. Teſ. 2.</note> indeuour to ſtoppe the mouthes of ſuch as wold clerely and openly publiſhe this doctrine, as the worthynes thereof requyreth. For wherin conſyſtethe the ſaluation of the
<pb facs="tcp:13033:21"/> faithfull,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> but in the free electy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of god? ſhould we not preache and declare, that god hathe cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen hys, throughe his free mercy withoute reſpecte of any thynge that is? ſhall we not ſuffer thys myſtery (hyghe though it be, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible thoughe it be) to be declared,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1</note> when as god wold haue it to be reueled? Truely it is an euydence, that we conſpyre with ſathan, to declare that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt hath ſuffered in vaine and that the paſſion which he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered profytethe the worlde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge, and that all wente to the deuyll and to deſtruction. This then is the fyrſte poynte whiche wee haue herein to obſerue and marke, that when we adnychy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the election of god, the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel can not be preached: for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute
<pb facs="tcp:13033:22"/> it, it is a baſtarde goſpell and a prophane: it is a doctryne of machomyte, there can be noo more churche nor chryſtyanitie, what ſhall then be ſayde?<note place="margin">Luke. 12</note> when we ſhal belie the holy ghoſt whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che here ſpeketh: when we go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to refuſe this doctryne. And therfore on our behalfe lette vs determyne<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> conſtantly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende it, for it is the grounde of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. How can we builde and maynteyne the buyldynge, when the foundation ſhalbe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen? Sayncte Paule cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs hereunto when he wil go about to ſhew bi what power we haue to fyghte, howe we ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre to this inherytaunce which hath ben ſo<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> derely bought for vs howe we enter into the glorye of god,<note place="margin">Luc. 14.</note> howe we ſhall fyniſhe this
<pb facs="tcp:13033:22"/> buyldynge. He ſayth, my frendes you muſte be founded vppon this grace whiche is not of to daye or yeſterdaye, but before the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world. True it is, that at this preſente god cauleth vs, but<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> the electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goth before: yea god elected vs beyng not moued thervnto throughe our deſertes, afore we coulde haue layd before hym any thyng at al, for we owe him al, he hath drawen vs<note place="margin">zach. 5.</note> from the goulfe of deſtruction where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we were drowned lyke poore deſperate creatures. It is then good reaſon<note place="margin">1 Pet. 9.</note> that we ſubmit our ſelues wholy vnto hym, accoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng our ſelfe<note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> al together bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to his goodneſſe, wherewith we ſhoulde be wholy rauyſhed. In this wiſe ſpeketh ſainct Paule. And ſo let vs hold faſt this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb facs="tcp:13033:23"/> (as I haue ſayde) excepte we wold that our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould runne into decaye and deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And to conclude, let vs note alſo that this doctryne is more then profytable, when it is well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed for oure vſage. They whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wolde we ſhoulde ſpeake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng at al of the election of god, wyl ſaye. Oh what, it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. But ſuche perſons neuer taſted of the goodneſſe of god, nor of the hope whiche we oughte to haue: lyttle knowe they what it is, not to goo to our lorde Ieſus Chryſte. For if wee knowe not, that we be ſaued for that it hathe pleaſed god<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> to chooſe vs before the creation of the worlde, howe ſhoulde we knowe that, whyche Sayncte Paule here reherſethe vnto vs, whiche is,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> that we be
<pb facs="tcp:13033:23"/> dedicated to God,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> for to be made apte and diſpoſed to lyue and dye in his ſeruice? Howe can we ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie his holye name? howe can we confeſſe that oure ſaluation proceadeth of hym alone? &amp; that he is the begynnynge? and that we haue not aſſyſted him therin? well we maye ſaye it with oure tongue, but it ſhalbe hypocritical<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſpoken, excepte we be reſolued vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this doctrin, as it is here ſet forth and declared. Let vs lerne therfore that this doctrine of the election of god, and by the why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we be taughte that he hathe predeſtinated vs before the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the worlde, that this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctryne (I ſaye)<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3</note> ought to be prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched boldely and playnely in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite of all the world which wold withſtand the ſame. And not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:24"/> that, but we knowe that it is an article more then profytable: for without that, wee can not ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually apprehende the infinite goodneſſe of oure god, vntyll we be brought ſo far: for a man ſhall but ſhadowe alwais the mercies of god, if we haue not this ſure prynciple and grounde, that he choſe vs<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> before we were borne, or could otherwyſe preuent him. And whye? thoughe men wolde ſay, we haue ben redemed by the bloudde of our lord Ieſus Chriſt and that we were vnworthye of his ſo gret mercy ſhewed vs, yet whoo is it (wyll they ſaye) that hath his parte and portion in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che redemption whiche god hath purchaſed in the perſon of his ſon but ſuche as wyl haue it, ſuch as ſeeke after god, ſuche as doo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte
<pb facs="tcp:13033:24"/> them ſelues, ſuche as be not too ſtubburne, ſuch as are of good inclynation and diſpoſition, they whiche haue ſome good deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? but when they ſhall meddle with the matter after ſuch a ſorte, and preſume to be cauled vnto god &amp; to his grace throughe any thyng procedynge of theym ſelues, or thyncke that they brought ſome gobet of their owne to part ſtake with god concernynge their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,<note place="margin">1. Co. 4.</note> it weare as much as to obſcure, yea to teare (as it were) in peces the grace of god, which is a ſacrilege not to be born with and therfore haue I ſayde, that the goodneſſe of god ſhal neuer be knowen at the full as it oughte, vntyl ſuche tyme as the election be layde before vs,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.</note> teſtyfiynge that we are at this inſtante cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13033:25"/>
            <head>Sonday the .v. of Maye. 1555. after dyner.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2. Tim. 1</bibl>
                  <p>¶ But be partaker of the afflyctions of the goſpel, through the power of god: who ſaued vs and cauled vs with an holy caulyng. Not accordynge to our dedes, but accordyng to his owne pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe and grace: whiche grace was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to vs throughe Chryſt Ieſus, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the worlde was. &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue declared this mornynge accordinge to the texte of Saynct Paule, that to knowe effectually goddes fre grace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge our ſaluation, we muſt haue recourſe to his eternal cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, by the whiche he dydde<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> choſe vs before the creation of the worlde: For therein we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde and ſee, that<note place="margin">Rom. 11 Ephe. 2.</note> he hadde no reſpecte to oure perſons, or to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dignitie that was in vs, nor
<pb facs="tcp:13033:25"/> to any merytes that wee coulde brynge hym. And why? becauſe that yer we were born, we were wrytten vp in his Regeſter, and he had alredye<note place="margin">Luc. 10. Rom. 8.</note> accepted vs for his chyldren. Therefore let vs lerne to attrybute the whole to his mercy, acknowledginge and teſtifienge, that on oure behalfe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> wee coulde not reioyce of anye thynge that was in vs, without derogation of the honour due vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to god. Trewe it is, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to mannes<note place="margin">Gene. 6.</note> wycked na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſome will cauyll to darken the grace of god: ſayenge, that thoughe god had choſen ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the creation of the world, he dyd it accordynge to that which he foreſawe they ſhoulde dyffer from thothers. Neuertheles the ſcripture ſheweth euidently, that
<pb facs="tcp:13033:26"/>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25</note> god ſtaieth not vntyll they can ſhewe them ſelues whether they be worthye or not, when he cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth theym: But the ſophiſters think, they can obſcure the grace of god: in ſaienge, that thought he regarded not the merites paſt yet rekeneth he vppon the meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that are to come. For (ſaye they) thoughe Iacob and Eſau his brother<note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> had doone no good nor euyll, yet god dyd choſe the one, and reiected the other: So he foreſawe (as<note place="margin">Heb. 4.</note> all thinges are preſente vnto hym) that Eſau wold be a wicked manne, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temner of all: and that Iacob wolde be ſuche one, as with the tyme he declared hym ſelfe. In this wiſe do ſuche perſonnes lay theyr foundation: but theſe are vaine imaginations, for they all
<pb facs="tcp:13033:26"/> together belie S. Paule,<note place="margin">Eph 1.2 2. Tim. 1</note> who proueth that God gaue noo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde to oure workes when he choſe vs, in aſmuch as that was decreed and done before the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the worlde. And thoughe the Auctoritie of S. Paul were not of force, yet is the matter ſoo euident, that they which thincke to eſcape throughe ſuche ſhyftes, ſhewe them ſelues very beaſtes, and as men to farre ouer ſene (I ſaye) not onely in the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of the ſcryptures, but alſo to be voyde of al reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For if we wold ſerche to finde out what is in man, what ſhal we find there?<note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> Is not the whole maſſe of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde accurſed?<note place="margin">Pſa. 51.</note> What brought we out of oure mothers wombe, but all iniquitie?<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.</note> We differ not at al then the one from the other
<pb facs="tcp:13033:27"/> but that it pleaſed god to gather vnto hym ſelfe<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> thoſe whom he wolde. And therefore vſeth S. Paule that worde in an other place of ſcripture, when he ſaith, that<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4</note> men haue not wherof to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyce, becauſe none ſhalbe founde to excell his neyghboure, but in that wherin we are dyſcerned of god. Seynge then it is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre offyce of God to diſcerne vs from them whiche abyde in their condemnation. Let vs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that all ſhoulde haue byn loſte,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cepte the remedy hadde come vnto vs by an other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. So then after we haue con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſed, that<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> god choſe vs before the worlde was made, it folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth therof, that he then prepared vs to receaue his grace, whiche he powred into vs that whiche
<pb facs="tcp:13033:27"/> was not there before: not that he onely<note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> choſe vs to be inhery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of his kyngdome, but that alſo immediatly he<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> marked vs, to thende we ſhoulde be iuſtifyed and gouerned by his holi ſpirite. This doctrine oughte to be ſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and reſolued vpon amonge Chriſtians, that if any deſpyſe it (as we ſe many at this preſente daye goo aboute to quenche and extinguiſhe the trueth of god) we oughte to acknowledge them to<note place="margin">Act. 7.</note> repyne or repugne agaynſte the holy ghoſt: yea to be as bulles and madde beaſtes, which wold vtterly ſet at naught all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcrypture. For in deede there hath bin more honeſtie in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtes then in them. For the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctryne of the papyſtes in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe is better, holyer, and farre
<pb facs="tcp:13033:28"/> awaye more conformable to the holye ſcrypture, then is that of theſe wycked wretches, whiche this day go about lyke barking dogges and hogges, that with theyr muſſels wold wrote vp al (as we maye ſee) to ouerthrowe and turne vp ſyde downe the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of god, whiche mennes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie to farre paſſeth meaſure. Wherfore come of it what wyll, let vs ſticke hard to the doctrine here declared. For ſeynge God had choſen vs<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> before the world had his courſe, let vs attribute the cauſe of our ſaluation to hys free goodneſſe. We ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> we ar not adopted by him accordinge to oure demery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: for we hadde nothyng, nor coulde bringe any thyng at all of oure owne vnto him. We muſte
<pb facs="tcp:13033:28"/> therefore aſcrybe the<note place="margin">Ebre. 5.</note> cauſe and ofſpringe of oure ſaluation to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in hym alone, and theron to grounde oure ſelues, for other wiſe al that euer we ſhal builde, wyll runne to ruine. But yet we muſte well note that which S. Paule here addethe: Fyrſte the grace of Ieſus Chryſt with the eternall counſayle of god his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And then how he bryngeth vs to oure vocation: to the ende we myghte be aſſured of goddes goodneſſe and good wyl<note place="margin">Colo. 1.</note> which had byn hyd from vs, excepte he had geuen vs a teſtimonie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For the fyrſt poynte then S. Paule ſayth, that the grace whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che dependeth of the onely pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of god and therein compry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is geuen vs in oure lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſt. As though he wold
<pb facs="tcp:13033:29"/> ſaye: For as muche as<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to be reiected and hated as mortall ennemies of god, it was of neceſſitie, that<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> we ſhoulde be graffed as it wer in Ieſus chriſt: to thende that god might recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſe and aduouche vs for his chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren. For when god reſpecteth vs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 30</note> he can not but deteſt vs, for that he findeth vs ful of pouerte, full of ſynne, and as it were ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vppe with all iniquitie. God who is the ſoueraygne Iuſtyce,<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.</note> can not entre into any maner of league or appointment with vs, whiles he beholdeth our nature. Where as he then wold choſe vs before the creation of the world, it was of neceſſitie,<note place="margin">1. Ti. 2.</note> that Ieſus Chriſte ſhoulde be there betwene bothe: to thende we myght be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in his perſone, for he was
<pb facs="tcp:13033:29"/> the wel be loued ſonne: and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god coupleth vs vnto him,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> then are we acceptable in his ſyghte. Let vs lerne then to be fully cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified of the election of god, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to make oure profyte, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctly to come to Ieſus Chryſte: for he is the<note place="margin">2. Co. 4. Colo. 1.</note> true glaſſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we may beholde oure election. If Ieſus Chriſte be take away, then remayneth God a iudge for ſynners, at whoſe handes we can not hope for fauour or good thing but rather wait for al ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance. His maieſtie alſo wyl be alwais terrible vnto vs<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> without Ieſus Chryſt. If any talke vnto vs of his eternall purpoſe, we ſhall be ſo aſtonyed, as thoughe he were in full redineſſe to caſt vs downe into hell. But when we ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.</note> in Chryſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth
<pb facs="tcp:13033:30"/> all grace, then maye we aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure oure ſelues, that god hathe loued vs, although we were not worthye therof. Let this ſerue for one ſpeciall poynte, touchyng that wherof S. Paul here ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. Secondarely that he here ſpeaketh not ſymplye of the elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of god (for that could not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficientely reſolue vs, but rather bryng vs into a greater perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie of mynde) But S. Paul ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the worde <hi>Vocation,</hi> by the which, god hath<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 1. Pet. 1.</note> manifeſted his counſayle, that before was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, and wherevnto we els coulde neuer aſpyre. Howe ſhall we then knowe, that we are elec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted of god, to thende we myghte reioyſe in hym, and glorye ouer the goodneſſe whiche he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueled vnto vs? Some ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:13033:30"/> of the election of god at auentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, leauyng the goſpel, leauing all that god layeth before vs, to brynge vs vnto hym ſelfe: yea al the meanes which he hath ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and knoweth to be meete for vs to put in vre. But we may not ſo procede: For we muſt (<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1 Rom. 8.</note>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to S. Paules rule) cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the vocation with the eternal election. Nowe this worde <hi>(Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation)</hi> ſignifyeth as muche as a caullynge. Trewe it is that the worde is taken out of the latine: yet ſuch as vnderſtand no latine, ought to knowe what the worde importeth. Now then it is ſaid, that we are cauled, which is the ſeconde worde. God then cauleth vs: But how? When it pleaſeth hym<note place="margin">1. Co. 2.</note> to certifie vs of oure electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whiche otherwiſe we ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:13033:31"/> neuer haue attayned vnto. For who euer entred into the councel of God?<note place="margin">Iſa. 40 Rom. 11.</note> as the prophete Iſaie &amp; S. Paule alſo dothe ſay. But when it pleaſeth god to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate hym ſelfe fyrſte of all vnto vs, then haue we that which ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth all the reaſon of man. For we haue a good witnes bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar and a faythefull: that is to ſaye,<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 1. Cor. 11</note> the holy ghoſte, which lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs vp aboue the world, and leadeth vs into the marueylous ſecretes of god. wherfore we mai not without great delyberation ſpeake of the election of god (as to ſaye, that we are predeſtyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) neither maye we (to be well aſſured of oure ſaluation) ſearche in the ayre, or at all aduentures, whether God accompteth vs of the numbre of hys or not. What
<pb facs="tcp:13033:31"/> then?<note place="margin">2 Co. 4.</note> we muſt loke vnto the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell whiche is opened and ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs: for there doth god mani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſte hym ſelfe to be oure father, and that he hath<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.</note> ſealed vs, to leade vs to the inherytaunce of life. And this knoweledge is a ſeale of the holy ghoſt in our har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and a ſure teſtimonye of oure ſaluation, ſo farre as we receaue hym by fayth. For the goſpell is preached to many, which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe are reprobates: nay god dothe vtter and declare, that he hath curſed them, that they haue no part nor portion in his kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, becauſe they do reſyſte the goſpel, and<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> refuſe the grace that is offered vnto them. But when we receaue in obedyence of fayth the doctryne of god, and reſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his promiſes, accepting the offer
<pb facs="tcp:13033:32"/> which he hath made<note place="margin">Gala. 4 Ephe. 1.</note> to hold vs for his chyldren, this (ſay I) is a trew<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1</note> certificate of our electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. yet haue we to note, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we knowe this oure ſaluation throughe this callynge, and that god hath illumynated vs in the faythe of his goſpell, it is not to adnichylate the euerlaſtyng pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination whiche wente before. For at this daye, a man ſhall ſee manye that wyll ſaye, who are they whom god hath choſen, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge the faythfull? I graunte. But lyke beaſts as they are they make an euill conſequence: that is to ſaye, that faythe ſhoulde be the cauſe of our ſaluation, yea the fyrſt cauſe. It is trewe in it ſelf, if they caule it the meane. For the ſcrypture ſayth,<note place="margin">Act. 15. Ephe. 2.</note> that we be ſaued throughe faythe: But we
<pb facs="tcp:13033:32"/> muſt aſcende higher. For if they attribute faythe to the free wyll of men, they wickedly blaſpheme agaynſt god, robbe god of his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, &amp; are in this behalfe worſe then the papyſtes, as I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redye ſayde. Wherfore we muſte otherwyſe talke of the matter,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> ſo farre as the ſcrypture geueth vs leaue: that is to ſaye, when god geueth vs fayth, it lyeth not in oure power to receaue the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel, but as he diſpoſeth it through his holy ſpyrite. For it ſuffyſeth vs not to haue oure eares beaten at with the voyce of a man. It ſhall be but a ſounde, whiche wil vanyſhe awaye with the wynde,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> excepte God worke inwardely, and ſpeake vnto vs after a more ſecrete maner throughe his holy ſpiryte. Note then, that frome
<pb facs="tcp:13033:33"/> thence procedeth the fayth. But who is the cauſe? Why is faythe geuen to one ſooner then to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?<note place="margin">Act. 13.</note> S. Luke hath declared, ſayinge, that they whiche were ordeyned to ſaluation, beleued the ſermon of Sayncte Paule. There were many hearers, and yet but ſome of them receued the promeſſe of ſaluation. But who were they? Suche as were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned to ſaluation, ſaith ſaincte Luke. What nedeth longer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation? And agayne Saynct Paule in the fyrſt chapter to the Epheſians<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> treateth hereof ſo at lengthe, that the ennemyes of goddes predeſtination muſte ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des be vtterly voide of ſence, and that the deuyll hath torne theyr eyes in ſondre, and be withoute vnderſtandyng. Yea wholly<note place="margin">Gala. 3.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:33"/> when they ſe not more in a matter ſo euydent. For S. Paule ſayth, that god hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs, and hath made vs parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kars of greate treaſures and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fynite rycheſſe opteyned for vs through oure lord Ieſus Chriſt. But howe? According (ſaith he) to that that he dyd chooſe vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the creation of the worlde. Sayncte Paule intreatinge of fayth, bryngeth vs backe to his prynciple, to leade vs hygher, to leade vs to the fyrſte cauſe, and to the fountayne of oure ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This is that fre grace, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue ſo often made mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. When then we ſay, that we<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> are cauled to ſaluation, and aſſured thereof, in as muche as god hath geuen vs the faythe, there is yet a cauſe hygher to be conſydered,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:34"/> that is, the election eternal. And who ſo wyl not aſcende thyther, derogateth from god his honour ſeing he can not diſcerne betwene man and man, otherwiſe then by theyr merytes and dyſpoſition that he ſeith in them. Thus muſt we then knytte together the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences or wordes, which ſaincte Paule here reherſeth, whiche is alſo to be ſeene throughoute the whole holy ſcrypture.</p>
            <p>Nowe then to make a bryefe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion: let vs take hede what ordre we oughte to obſerue in ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chyng out for our ſaluation. We may not begynne at this pointe, as to ſaye, are we elected or not? No, no,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> For we ſhall neuer aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de nor aproche ſo nere the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of god, but that we ſhall be<note place="margin">Pro. 25.</note> in daunger to be confounded an
<pb facs="tcp:13033:34"/> hundreth thouſande tymes, and to be vtterly depryued of all our ſenſes. Howe ſhall we then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceade?<note place="margin">Hebr. 2.</note> Let vs geue eare to that whiche is ſpoken vnto vs in the goſpell, howe that god hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs the grace to receaue the promes whiche he offreth vs, knowynge that it ſtandeth vs in as muche ſtede, as if he had ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his hearte and inrolled oure election in our conſciences, Note therfore howe we muſte be certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> that god hath adopted vs for his chyldren, and that<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> the inheritaunce of the kyngdome of heauen is vnfaynedly oures: in that (I ſaye) that wee be cauled in Ieſus Chryſte. Howe ſhal we knowe it? Howe ſhal we be ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon the doctryne whiche god layeth before our eyes? We muſt
<pb facs="tcp:13033:35"/> immediately (for the better ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifyenge of the grace of God)<note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> acknowledge, that wee canne brynge nothyng on our part, but ſo to abaſe vs, withoute chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge ſo muche as one droppe of prayſe towardes our ſelues, that wee acknowledge<note place="margin">2. Teſ. 2</note> god to haue cauled vs nowe to the goſpel, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to that he dyd<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> choſe vs before the creation of the world. Nowe trewe it is, that this elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God is as it were clooſe letters: yea to vs, for that it con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſteth in it ſelfe, and in his owne nature. But therin may we rede becauſe that god geueth a teſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony vnto vs,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> when he cauleth vs vnto hym ſelfe throughe the knowledge of the goſpell, and throughe faythe. Then haue we therby<note place="margin">Deut. 17</note> a double or copie geuen
<pb facs="tcp:13033:35"/> vs. For like as the Origynal or pryncipall Regeſter derogateth nothyng from the copie or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente whiche ſhall be redde, but is rather an approbation of the ſame: and none wyll ſearche out for the oryginall, when he hathe the copie autentique:<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.</note> Euen ſoo muſte we be aſſured of our electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For when god certifieth vs by his goſpell,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> that he accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs for his chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they are letters autentique, ſigned<note place="margin">Hebr. 9.</note> with the bloudde of oure lorde Ieſus Chryſt, and<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> ſealed with his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpyrite. When we haue that, haue we not ſuffyciently where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to be contented? Now then as I haue ſayde, ſo farre wide is the election of god from contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryeng this poynte, that it rather ratifyeth and confyrmeth the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie
<pb facs="tcp:13033:36"/> whiche we haue in the goſpell. Not that we haue neede to loke into the orygynall or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſter of god, as thoughe there were ſome doubte. We haue the inſtrumente which can not faile: what wolde we more?<note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> Shall it not be ouer great raſhnes who wyll demaund more? Who wyll aſcende<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> vp aboue the clowdes, when we haue the worde in our mouthe and in oure hearte<note place="margin">Deu. 30.</note> as Moſes ſaithe? Trewe it is, that if we thoughte the inſtrumente wer not taken out of the true Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſter &amp; Orygynall, then might a man cal it in queſtion or doubt. But when the thynge is playne and certayne, what wolde wee more? So fareth it with vs, that we nede no more to doubte, but that<note place="margin">Luc. 10.</note> god hath inrolled vs in the
<pb facs="tcp:13033:36"/> numbre of his elect and children<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> before the creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world.<note place="margin">Colo. 1.</note> But he kepte the matter ſecrete vnto hym ſelfe: Yet haue wee in the meane time letters patentes of oure ſaluation.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note> We haue an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſure inough as I haue declared alredye. But yet muſte we alwaies<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> reſorte to oure lord Ieſus Chryſte, when there is queſtion of oure election. For<note place="margin">Io. 10.14.</note> without hym (as I haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed) we can not approche neere vnto god. And agayne, when we ſhal ſpeake of his decree, we ſhal be aſtonyed as coulpable of deth. But hauynge Ieſus Chryſte for oure guyde,<note place="margin">Ro.. 5.8.</note> we maye boldelye reioyce, knowyng howe that he hath<note place="margin">Heb. 3. Ap. 4.5.</note> dignitie and worthyneſſe inoughe in hym ſelfe, to make all his membres acceptable to god
<pb facs="tcp:13033:37"/> his father. It ſuffiſeth, that we be<note place="margin">Ephe. 4</note> graffed in his body, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto hym. Nowe ſe ye, howe we oughte to meditate this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, if we lyſte to do therwith oure profyte, accordynge to that whiche is here declared vnto vs by ſayncte Paule,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1</note> Who ſaythe, that this grace was geuen vs. And howe before al tymes ſaith he. We muſte aſcende aboue the courſe of nature, when we wyll go aboute to knowe howe we be ſaued, and for what cauſe, and whence it ſhuld procede. And far<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der we muſte vnderſtande, that god wold not leaue vs in ſuſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<note place="margin">Mat. 11. Ioh. 17.</note> nor yet wolde he hide his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle frome vs, to brynge vs in doubte of oure ſaluation. But he hath<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> cauled vs to hym ſelfe: not onely by preaching of the goſpel,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:37"/> (for that had not ben ſuffyciente) but<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> he ſealed in oure heartes the teſtymonie of his goodneſſe and fatherly loue. So then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue ſuche a certaynetie, let vs fyrſte of all<note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> gloryfie god, for that he hath cauled vs throughe his free mercye. And farder wee muſte ſtaye oure ſelues vpon our lorde Ieſus Chryſte, acknowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge, that he deceaued vs not of oure expectation, when he cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed to be publyſhed, that he<note place="margin">Gala. 1.</note> gaue hym ſelfe to vs, teſtyfienge alſo the ſame vnto vs<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> by the holye ghoſte. For fayth is to vs (as I haue alredye ſayde) an infallible marke, that<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.</note> god rekeneth vs for his chyldren, beynge conducted thence to the eternall election. And wherfore? God hath cauled vs (ſaythe ſayncte Paule in the
<pb facs="tcp:13033:38"/> fyrſte chapiter to the Epheſians)<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> according to that he forechoſe vs He ſaythe not that god choſe vs becauſe we harde the goſpel: but contrary wiſe he geueth faythe, whiche for this ſpeciall cauſe is geuen vs, to declare, that<note place="margin">Rom 5.</note> God reſerued vs to ſaue vs when we were loſte and caſte awaye in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. Farder we haue to note, that ſaincte Paule ſpeaketh not here of others then the faythful. But ſome blocke heades ther be, whiche to blynde the eyes of the ignoraunte and ſuch as they are, wyll here cauyll, that the grace of ſaluation was geuen vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe god had ordeyned, that his ſonne ſhuld be the redemer of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde, and that the ſame was commen and indifferent vnto al. But ſaincte Paule hath ſo vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:13033:38"/> his ſpeche, that his doctryne can not with ſuche chyldiſhe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be corrupted. For notably<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1 Tit. 3.</note> he ſayde before, that god hath ſaued vs. Is that referred indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to al without exception?<note place="margin">1. Ti. 4.</note> No, no: he ſpeketh but of the faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Cauled he all the worlde? Some<note place="margin">Ma. 22. Luc. 14.</note> were cauled by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng, but yet they ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues vnworthy of that ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whiche was offerid them and therfore wer reproued.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> Others ſome god lefte in theyr increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, who neuer hearde ſo muche as one worde of the goſpel prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. So then ſainct Paule doth ſpecially adreſſe hym ſelfe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom god had choſen and reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to hym ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And therfore let vs holde thys pryncyple, that the goodneſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:13033:39"/> god ſhall neuer be perfectely and worthelye honoured as it deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, except we knowe that<note place="margin">Act 17. Gala. 1.</note> god wolde vs not to abyde &amp; remaine in the commen deſtruction of the worlde, wherein he hathe lefte them whiche were like vnto vs, and from whom we dyffered in nothynge,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> beynge of nature no better then they were: But<note place="margin">Luc. 12.</note> ſuch was his good wyl and pleaſure. Wherfore<note place="margin">Rom. 3</note> let all men ſtop their mouthes herat, and no man pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſume to attrybute any thynge to hym ſelfe: geuynge in the meane tyme god the prayſe with open mouthe,<note place="margin">Dani. 9.</note> confeſſyng, that to him we owe all that concerneth oure ſaluation. This is the ſumme of all that whiche wee haue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne and kepe in memory. But in the meane while, let vs note
<pb facs="tcp:13033:39"/> well the other wordes whyche S. Paule vſeth here. Trewe it is, that in effecte he vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the ſame that we haue alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die declared, that the election of God ſhoulde not profyte vs nor come vnto vs, excepte we hadde knowne it, whiche by meanes of the goſpell is made knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. For this cauſe<note place="margin">Mat. 11.</note> wold god haue that manyfeſted vnto vs,<note place="margin">Colo. 1.</note> which he kept as it were ſecret to hym ſelfe before al times. But (for the better expreſſynge of his minde) he enterlaceth as it were by the way, to declare, that<note place="margin">Tit. 2.</note> this grace was now reueled vnto vs. And howe? In the apperyng of oure Lorde Ieſus Chryſte. He ſheweth, that we ſhal be to farre vnkynde, vnleſſe that herewith we can be contented and at reſte.
<pb facs="tcp:13033:40"/> When the ſonne of God<note place="margin">Ephe. 5. Gala, 1.</note> geueth hym ſelfe vnto vs, what can we deſyre more? Thoughe we could mounte vp aboue the clowdes, and coulde entre into the mooſte depe ſecretes of god, what ſhall be the ende thereof? Is it not to knowe, that we are his chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and heyres? That nowe is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientlye manifeſted and declared in Chryſte Ieſu, for it is ſayde, that<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> all they whiche beleue in hym, ſhall enioye this priuilege, to be made the chyldren of God. Wee maye not therefore declyne (the leaſt thing that can be) from Ieſus Chryſte, if we wyll be ful certifyed of our election. Trewe it is, that ſaynct Paule hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready declared, that we were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beloued nor choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1. Colo, 1.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in the perſon of Ieſus chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:13033:40"/> his onely ſonne. But he now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a more ample declaration, when he ſayth, that Ieſus chriſt after he appered, hathe<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.</note> opened vnto vs the life which otherwiſe ſhuld haue ben vnknowne to vs. He hath preſented vs the grace of god,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> from the which we were otherwiſe farre of. He hath made vs ſo familiar with god, that we knowe what is his euerlaſtyng counſayle, without<note place="margin">Eccle. 3. Rom. 12.</note> ſerchyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue oure reache, that whiche is not laufull for vs to enquyre of. For when god wyll inſtructe vs by his owne propre mouthe, we maye not preſume to wade ſo far as they whiche walke not vnder obedience: For it is a preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſeke to know more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god wyll permytte. But<note place="margin">1. Pe.</note> when we walke ſoberly and with reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:13033:41"/> vnder the obedience of our God, geuinge audyence &amp; receaue that whiche he vttereth in holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as I haue alredy ſayd,<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.</note> the waye ſhall be made meete for vs to wade throughe withall.</p>
            <p>Marke then ſaincte Paule whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſayth, that the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.</note> by his apperance in the world, opened oure eyes, to the ende we ſhoulde knowe the grace<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs before the begynnyng of the worlde: As to be receaued for chyldren of God, to be made acceptable vnto hym, and<note place="margin">Ephe. 1. 2. Cor. 5.</note> to be accompted as iuſte, in ſuch wiſe, that we nede not to doubte, the<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. 1.</note> inheritaunce is made ready for vs in the kyngedome of heauen.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.</note> Not that we haue it for any me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytes of ours, but for that Ieſus Chryſt had the right title, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:13033:41"/> he hath made vs participante.</p>
            <p>And where as it is here ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the appering of Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> we muſt referre that to the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, becauſe ſayncte Paule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth herewith that throughe the goſpell he broughte lyfe and immortalitie to light. For howe appered Ieſus Chryſt vnto vs? As he appereth euery daye. But yet ſaynct Paule wolde not dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thoſe thynges that the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſetteth forth for the aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our ſaluation whiche is layde vppe in Ieſus Chriſte. It is not ſayde in one worde, that Ieſus Chryſte is oure ſauyoure, that he was ſente as the lieutenaunte of god his father. No? no? It is ſayde, that he was ſente as the<note place="margin">Rom. 3. Hebr. 9.</note> mediatoure, which hath recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyled vs by the ſacryfyce of hys
<pb facs="tcp:13033:42"/> deathe: He was ſent vs,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> as the lambe without ſpotte, to pourge and make ſatisfaction for al our dettes: He is oure pledge, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer vs<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> from the condempna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of deathe, wherin we were: He is<note place="margin">1. Io. 2.</note> our iuſtice, our aduocate, which maketh interceſſion in our name:<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> whiche wyll brynge to paſſe, that oure prayers ſhall be hearde of god: which is the band of concorde betwene god and vs: which hath opteyned for vs, that whiche apperteyned not vnto vs by nature. For all theſe qualy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties muſt we attrybute to Ieſus Chryſte, if we wyll effectuallye knowe howe he appeared. For if we ſhoulde but ſymplye take the goſpell, and not haue regarde to the ſubſtance therein conteyned: that were inoughe to ouerthrow
<pb facs="tcp:13033:42"/> all, and in effect, we ſhould make of Ieſus Chryſte but as it were a ſhadowe. For if we ſaye, that Ieſus Chryſte hath appeared to be oure ſauiour, without menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on makynge of that whiche he ſuffered for our ſaluation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare not howe we haue ben<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concyled into the fauoure of god his father throughe and by hys meanes: that we<note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> haue ben clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from our filthynes and ſpots: that we haue ben redemed<note place="margin">Colo. 2.</note> from the oblygation of euerlaſtynge death. If we haue not that with all, what auayleth it? If wee knowe not<note place="margin">Heb. 7.9.</note> that Ieſus Chryſte is oure aduocate, and that he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryeth our prayers whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we praie to god, to thende we ſhoulde not be repulſed, what ſhal become of vs? What truſt were there to cal
<pb facs="tcp:13033:43"/> vpon the name of god, whiche is<note place="margin">Pro. 18.</note> the fortreſſe of ſaluation, as the ſcripture ſayth? Let vs note wel then, that ſayncte Paule ſaythe that Ieſus Chryſt hath<note place="margin">Hebr. 9.</note> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he meaneth chiefly, that he hathe accomplyſhed all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that were requiſite for the redemption of mankinde. But by the waye he ſettethe forthe the<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> vertue of this bryghtneſſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath appeared vnto vs in his reſurrection: to thende we ſhulde be partakers of ſoo great a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, and ſo to enioye the ſame.</p>
            <p>Nowe if the goſpell were taken awaye, what coulde the bytter deathe whiche the ſonne of God ſuffered, and his ryſynge againe on the thyrde daye, auayle vs? All ſhulde be vnprofytable vnto vs.<note place="margin">1. Co. 4.15 Ephe. 3.</note> The goſpell then puttethe
<pb facs="tcp:13033:43"/> vs in poſſeſſion of thoſe rycheſſe, whiche Ieſus Chryſte hath op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned and procured for vs. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne,<note place="margin">Colo. 3.</note> thoughe he be nowe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente in body, and is not here in this earth conuerſaunt with vs, let vs thynke oure ſtate therfore neuer a whit the worſe. For<note place="margin">Mat. 28</note> he hath not ſo withdrawne him ſelf that we ſhoulde ſeeke hym, and not fynde hym. For the Sonne whiche ſhyneth, doth not ſo clere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly gyue lyghte to the worlde, as<note place="margin">Io. 14.</note> Ieſus Chryſte doth manyfeſtly ſhewe hym ſelfe to theym whiche haue the eyes of fayth to beholde him, when the goſpel is preched. And that is the reaſon wherfore ſaynct Paule (beſides this word <hi>appearynge</hi>) ſaythe, that Ieſus hath brought to lyght that lyfe, yea the lyfe euerlaſtyng. But to
<pb facs="tcp:13033:44"/> the ende we may fynde in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wordes of ſayncte Paule, all that I haue ſayde, let vs marke well and followe that whiche is conteyned in this place of ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. He ſaythe, that the ſonne of god hath<note place="margin">Heb. 2.</note> deſtroyed deathe: but howe deſtroyed he it? If he had not offered the euerlaſtyng ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> appeaſynge of godds wrathe: If he had not deſcended<note place="margin">Eph. 4.</note> downe to the loweſte place, to drawe vs out from thence: If he had not taken<note place="margin">Gala. 3.</note> our curſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him for the dyſchargynge of vs, and had not taken away<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> the burthen vnder the whiche we beganne to ſyncke. What had it byn? Shuld deathe haue ben deſtroyed? No: death had had the dominion ouer vs, deathe had raygned immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ouer vs. And truely if eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:13033:44"/> one of vs wold enter into him ſelfe, we ſhal fynde, that<note place="margin">Ebre. 2.</note> we are of nature the ſlaues of Sathan, who is the prince of deth. Thus had we ben ſhut vp in this myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable bondage, excepte<note place="margin">Oſe. 13.</note> that god had deſtroyed the deuil, ſyn, and deathe. And that is doone: But howe? In that that through the bloud of our lorde Ieſus Chryſt,<note place="margin">Colo. 2.</note> he hath blotted out all our ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Nowe thoughe we be poore ſynners, and in daunger of the iudgemente of god, yet can<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> not ſynne hurte vs: becauſe the ſting where the poiſon lay, is ſo thruſt away,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> that it can not pricke vs, for nowe hath Chryſt the vycto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye: for he ſuffered not in vayne, the ſheddynge of his bloudde fell not on the earthe, nor at all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures: but it hath ben a laua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb facs="tcp:13033:45"/> wherwith we haue ben ſpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keled by the holy ghoſt, as ſainct Peter hath declared.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> Soo then we ſee well, that ſayncte Paule intreatyng of the goſpell, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Ieſus Chryſte hath appeared, and dayly dothe appeare vnto vs putteth not in forgetfulneſſe hys deathe and paſſion, nor any thing elles apperteynyng to the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankynde. We muſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore note theſe two thynges: that is, that in the perſonne of Ieſus Chryſte<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> we haue (all the ſorte of vs) that which we can deſire. We haue a ful &amp; an aſſured truſte of the goodneſſe of god, and of the loue whiche he bare vnto vs:</p>
            <p>And howe? Se we not, how our<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.</note> ſynnes haue ſeparated vs from god, and that they are the cauſe of continual warre and enmitie?
<pb facs="tcp:13033:45"/> But<note place="margin">Rom 3</note> we haue the attonemente in oure lorde Ieſus Chryſte: for<note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> he hath ſhed his bloud to waſhe vs from all oure fylthyneſſe. He hath offered a ſacryfyce, by the whiche God is at one wyth vs:<note place="margin">Pſa. 68.</note> He hathe payed al oure dettes: To be ſhorte, he hath<note place="margin">Gala. 3.</note> adnychy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the curſe, to the ende wee ſhoulde be bleſſed of god. And far<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, he hath<note place="margin">Heb. 2.</note> vanquyſed death, and triumphed ouer her, to the ende we might be deliuered from the tyranny whiche was in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyneſſe, wholly to ſwalowe vs vp: he hath ſtrength to ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t all. By this then we ſee all the thinges which apperteine to our ſaluation, to haue ben<note place="margin">Colo. 2.</note> accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in oure Ieſus Chryſte, and that there throughe we enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poſſeſſion of al his goodes.
<pb facs="tcp:13033:46"/> Let vs note, that dayely he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth vnto vs through his goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel. Trewe it is, that<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> he dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in his heauenly glorye: we ſhall not ſe him here in this earth viſiblye, but<note place="margin">Mat. 28</note> yet wyll he not be farre of from vs, neyther neede we make longe compaſes to ſeke hym. Lette vs open the eyes of faythe, and we ſhall ſe hym ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſtynge hym ſelfe vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Thus haue we learned out of the texte of ſaynct Paule, al that which I haue touched. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs lerne, not to ſeperate that whiche the holy ghoſt hath conioyned. Furthermore let vs note, that ſayncte Paule here by the waye of comparyſon, wolde amplifie the grace whiche God hath ſhewed to the world ſithens the commynge of our lord Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:13033:46"/> Chryſt. As though he wold ſay, that<note place="margin">Luke. 10</note> the aunciente fathers had not this aduantage, for that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſte appeared not vnto theym as vnto vs. Trewe it is,<note place="margin">1. Co. 10.</note> they had the ſame fayth, and the inherytance of heauen was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to them as vnto vs, in that god reueled vnto them his grace, as wel as vnto vs, but not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch meaſure. For<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> they ſawe Chryſt afarre of, and as it were in a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, as ſayncte Paule ſaythe, vnder the fygures of the lawe. There was the vaile of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which was ſo ſtretched forth that<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note> the Iewes coulde not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche to the materyall ſaynctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arye. But now that the vaile of the temple is broken, we maye approche to the maieſtie of oure god We come vnto heauen with
<pb facs="tcp:13033:47"/> full pryuylege, and then immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately we haue the lyuely ymage of god, wherein dwelleth all the perfection of glorye. To be ſhort:<note place="margin">Colo. 2.</note> we haue the body, where as the fathers had but the ſhadowe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as ſayncte Paule ſpeaketh to the Coloſſians. Nowe then wee are therby warned, that if the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of olde had ſuche conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and inuyncible zeale, to<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure and abyde in the afflyctions of the ſonne of god, beynge as yet not reueled to the worlde as at this daye, ſhall we not be of to fainte a courage, if we be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with a more ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t zeale? The aunciente fathers dyd fully reſolue them ſelues, to beare the afflyctions of Ieſus Chryſt, as it is ſayde in the eleuenth chapyter to the Hebrewes. For it is not
<pb facs="tcp:13033:47"/> ſayde, that Moiſes bare the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke of Abraham his father, but of Ieſus Chryſt. Note then that the auncient fathers, althoughe<note place="margin">1. Co. 10.</note> they lyued vnder the darke ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of the lawe, yet preſented they them ſelues vnto god in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfice, to<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> endure with much pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cience the afflyctions of Chriſte. But nowe<note place="margin">1. Co. 15</note> that Chryſte is ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen agayne from the deadde, and hath made open this life vnto vs what ſhall be ſayd of vs, if we be ſo delycate, that we can not beare the afflyctions of the goſpel? Are we not worthy to be raſed out of the Regeſter of god, and not to be auowed of hym. And therfore let vs loke vnto it: for<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> we ought to be ſoo encouraged with ſuche conſtancie of faythe, as to endure for the name of Ieſus Chryſte,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:48"/> what ſo euer pleaſeth god to laye vpon vs, ſeyng that lyfe is made manyfeſte before oure eyes, and that we haue a<note place="margin">Luk. 10.</note> better and more familiar knowledge therof, then had the auncyente fathers. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of the Apoſtle in his Epyſtle to the Hebrues ſpeakethe,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> where we reade that the auncyente fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers neuer ſhronke, but had ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a marueilous conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, that the hearyng therof were inough to aſtonyſhe vs. For wee knowe howe they were tormented by ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes and ennemyes of the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, and yet conſtantely ſuffered the ſame. The ſtate of the church is at this preſent daie no harder, nor more trobleſome, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was than. And ſeynge it ſo is, ſhal we make it more ſtrange, to followe after Chryſte Ieſus, who hathe
<pb facs="tcp:13033:48"/> ſhewed vs the waye? But to the ende we be not to fearefull nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer cold, let vs marke wel howe<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1</note> he ſaythe, that Ieſus Chryſte hath made manyfeſt the life and immortalytie throughe the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, for that that as often as the grace of god is preched vnto vs, it is as much as if the kyngdom of heauen were opened vnto vs, as if god ſtretched forth his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and certyfyed vs, that the life is at hande, and that he wyl parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate vnto vs of his heauenly in herytaunce. For that is ſpoken vnto vs, to the ende that vntyll we haue ſene Ieſus Chryſte lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge vs vp with hym, and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng vs vnto a lyfe certayne, we ſhoulde contente our ſelues with this preſent lyfe. We wold glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remayne here in this worlde,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:49"/>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 9.</note> but by force muſt we be drawen hence. But when we ſhal behold the lyfe whiche our lorde Ieſus Chryſt hath opteyned for vs, we<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> ſhall ſette but lyttle by all that myghte reteyne vs here, conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deryng we haue to aſcende vp to heauen. Soo then let vs not be wyllyngely blynde, when Ieſus Chryſte ſetteth dayly before our eyes the lyfe and immortalytie, whiche we haue ſpoken of. But let vs note wel, that when ſainct Paule ſpeaketh of the lyfe, and addeth the worde <hi>immortalitie,</hi> that it betokeneth as muche, as if he ſayde: We entre euen nowe into the kyngedome of god tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe faythe. For thoughe we be as<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2</note> ſtraungers here in thys earthe, and that it ſeemeth there is but deathe and maledyction in
<pb facs="tcp:13033:49"/> vs, yet wyll the lyfe and grace, wherof we are made partakers throughe our lord Ieſus Chriſt, brynge forthe his fruyte in hys conuenient tyme: that is to ſay, when he ſhall be<note place="margin">Mat. 25</note> ſent agayne of god his Father, to ſhewe vs the effect of ſuch thinges as are day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preached vnto vs, and which haue ben accompliſhed in his per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, when he was clothed wyth oure nature.</p>
            <p>Nowe to ende, lette vs<note place="margin">pſal. 95</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate oure ſelues before the face of our good God, acknowlegyng our faultes, deſyryng him that it wolde pleaſe hym, ſo to cauſe vs<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> feele our pouerties, that we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſo preſumptuouſe, as<note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> to attrybute any glorye vnto oure ſelues: but that we<note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> acknowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge oure ſelues, to be ſtinking
<pb facs="tcp:13033:50"/> and deteſtable in oure nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hym, to the ende we maye ſearche the whole cauſe of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation in his purpoſe and in that counſayle whiche hath ben reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, through the<note place="margin">Colo. 1.</note> knoweledge of the grace by hym opteined, when he cauled vs to his goſpell: And that alſo he wolde voucheſafe to graunt vs this benefite, that we maye adreſſe oure ſelues to oure lorde Ieſus Chryſt, and wholly to ſtay and reſte our ſelues vpon hym and the redemption whiche he purchaſed for vs: to the ende we maye be auowed for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, to be made partakers of the inherytaunce of lyfe, after we haue foughte in this worlde. And for as muche as it pleaſeth hym, that we ſhould be aſſaulted of Sathan and of ſo many enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb facs="tcp:13033:50"/> as wel domeſtical as ſtran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers,<note place="margin">1. Co. 10. Eph. 6.</note> That he wolde geue vs power to withſtand their aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: ſo as we be neuer left of him vntyll we haue ended our courſe. And that we be come to that reſt, vnto the whiche we are day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye conducted. And that this Grace be not onely ſhewed vnto vs, but to all people and nations of the earthe. &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13033:51"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprynted at London by VVyllyam Séres dvvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the vveſt ende of Paules churche at the ſygne of the hedgehogge.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13033:51"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
